<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lamentation of Melpomene, for the death of Belphæbe our late Queene With a ioy to England for our blessed King. / By T.W. Gentleman.</title>
            <author>T. W., gentleman.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14607</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24918</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111560</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846872</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846872</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11867</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14607)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11867)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1014:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lamentation of Melpomene, for the death of Belphæbe our late Queene With a ioy to England for our blessed King. / By T.W. Gentleman.</title>
                  <author>T. W., gentleman.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By W. W[hite] for C. K[night] at the signe of the Holy Lambe in S. Paules Church-yarde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Melpomenes lamentation, for the death of Belphæbe.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603 --  Death and burial --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11867:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Lamentation of Melpomene, for the death of <hi>BELPHAEBE</hi> our late Queene.</p>
            <p>With a Ioy to England for our bleſſed KING.</p>
            <p>By T. W. Gentleman.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of William White (1577?-1617) of a chariot drawn by dragons, the driver presumably being Triptolemus or Demeter</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by W. W. for C. K. at the ſigne of the Holy Lambe in S. Paules Church-yarde. 1603.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11867:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11867:2"/>
            <l>HE that to pleaſe a multitude, his ſtudies would imploy,</l>
            <l>A Faggot euen as well may bring, to burne bright burning <hi>Troy.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The auncient Poet <hi>Perſius,</hi> moſt wiſely ſay'd, I tro:</l>
            <l>Velle fuum cuique eſt, nec voto vinitur vno.</l>
            <l>So diuers is the mindes of men; ſome will haue this, ſome that:</l>
            <l>Some verſe, ſome proſe: &amp; ſome againe, wold haue they know not what</l>
            <l>Therefore I care not who finde fault, let who liſt laugh and ſcoffe:</l>
            <l>Let him that likes it, reed the ſame: he that diſliks, looke off.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:11867:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:11867:3"/>
            <head>The Lamentation of MELPOMENE, for the death of <hi>BELPHAEBE,</hi> our late Queene.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> In what vncoth place or gloomie Cell,</l>
            <l>Shall ſad <hi>Melpomenes</hi> tragicke ſpirit dwell?</l>
            <l>The chearful day torments my chearles hart,</l>
            <l>And euery ſplendent ſtar woundes like a dart.</l>
            <l>If euer Muſe had cauſe to mourne in deed,</l>
            <l>Now fits the time: and now the hart ſhould bleed:</l>
            <l>Now ſhould each member ioyne it ſelfe in one,</l>
            <l>And make a ſymphacie of griefe, and mone.</l>
            <l>Let coloured Silkes be dy'd to ſable blacke:</l>
            <l>A Mourning habite fits each Mourners backe.</l>
            <l>Day change thy ſelfe to euerlaſting Night,</l>
            <l>Sunne, Moone, and Starres, forgoe your glitt'ring light,</l>
            <l>Diſſolue you Mountaines, and you durate Rockes,</l>
            <l>Lament you Shepheards, and your tender Flockes:</l>
            <l>Let Teares diſtill in ſuch a bundant wiſe,</l>
            <l>That like the Ocean billowes they may riſe.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Caos,</hi> not <hi>Coſmos</hi> let the World be cleaped,</l>
            <l>Let woe on woe, and care on care be heaped:</l>
            <l>For loe; the Lampe that whilome burnt ſo cleare,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11867:4"/>
Is quite extinct, and darkneſſe doth appeare.</l>
            <l>A glorious Lampe; a goodly Light it was,</l>
            <l>Which whil'ſt it burnt, all other did ſurpaſſe.</l>
            <l>No place ſo farre remote but day, and night</l>
            <l>It was illuminated with this Light.</l>
            <l>Whilome it was the chiefeſt light alone</l>
            <l>Of England, Fraunce, Ireland, and Calydone.</l>
            <l>Few Lampes like this (yea few) or none at all</l>
            <l>Are worthy of the like memoriall.</l>
            <l>The chaſt <hi>Belphaebe</hi> is of life depriu'de,</l>
            <l>Merrour of Chaſtetie, when ſhee ſuruiu'de:</l>
            <l>Shee like a Roſe mong'ſt many weedes was placed,</l>
            <l>They grace'd by her, and ſhee by them diſgraced.</l>
            <l>Therefore the Fates ſuppoſ'd the earth too bace</l>
            <l>To ſuccour one of ſuch immortall race:</l>
            <l>And for a plague to men ſent meager Death,</l>
            <l>To take away her ſweete Ambroſian breath.</l>
            <l>What hart ſo hardie? (if it mortall beene)</l>
            <l>But will lament the death of ſuch a Queene,</l>
            <l>Which like a Goddeſſe, not an earthly creature,</l>
            <l>Appeared both in hauiour, and in feature.</l>
            <l>Prudence, and Conſtancie poſſeſt her minde;</l>
            <l>A rare memoriall for all women-kinde:</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11867:4"/>
No vertuous lore, ne well beſeeming graces,</l>
            <l>But liu'd in her, each in their ſeuerall places.</l>
            <l>The Fates had choſen her Earths Soueraigne,</l>
            <l>And by the Fates, Earth hath her loſt againe.</l>
            <l>After long darkneſſe on the earth, came light,</l>
            <l>And now againe enſewes eternall night:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Dianas</hi> ſiſter Lady of the day,</l>
            <l>From earth to heauen hath tane herſpeedy way;</l>
            <l>Second to none in Wiſedome ſure was ſhee,</l>
            <l>The Queene ſhe was of true feminitie.</l>
            <l>Well could I wiſh if Deſtenies thought good,</l>
            <l>Her habitation on <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> ſtood:</l>
            <l>And that from <hi>Ioues</hi> great Court ſhe were accited,</l>
            <l>And with my ſiſters in pure zeale vnited.</l>
            <l>Neuer till now did griefe my hart ſurpreſſe,</l>
            <l>And now tis cloy'd with too much heauineſſe:</l>
            <l>I muſt reſigne my place: I cannot chuſe,</l>
            <l>And beare no more the name of Tragicke Muſe;</l>
            <l>For I am Metamorphiſed with griefe;</l>
            <l>Griefe without end, and endleſſe to reliefe.</l>
            <l>If Heauen, or Hell, do harbour any ſoule</l>
            <l>Whoſe hart is made of ſuch a ſenceleſſe moule,</l>
            <l>That Death and Hell; that God, or cruell Fate,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11867:5"/>
Cannot with true compaſſion annimate,</l>
            <l>Let him poſſeſſe my place vpon the Hill:</l>
            <l>For Ile reſigne it with a right goodwill.</l>
            <l>Ile trauerſe through the world in Pilgrimage,</l>
            <l>And vnder-take <hi>Belphaebes</hi> Patronage;</l>
            <l>Ile maſſecar my ſelfe, lament, and mone,</l>
            <l>Whil'ſt there remaines no day to tell but one,</l>
            <l>In the remoteſt place from any wight,</l>
            <l>Where neither Sunne nor Moone do lend their light:</l>
            <l>There will I make a cloſe-light ſhadowing Cell,</l>
            <l>And till Times date be out, I there will dwell,</l>
            <l>Dreaming on horrors, gaſtly ſightes, and feares:</l>
            <l>Sadde thoughtes and I will liue eſpouſed Spheares.</l>
            <l>Ile teach the Screechowle, and the hisſing Snake,</l>
            <l>To beare a burden to the mone I make:</l>
            <l>Ile learne the Syluaine Birdes to hand their winges,</l>
            <l>When once my melancholie Organt ſinges</l>
            <l>Sadde Canticles, of her immortall prayſe,</l>
            <l>Who lyuing, bleſt the world with golden dayes.</l>
            <l>Both Peace and Iuſtice flouriſh'd in her age:</l>
            <l>Such was her foreſight, ſuch her counſaile ſage,</l>
            <l>If Vertue, Learning, Manners, Beautie, Witte,</l>
            <l>Immortall fame to mortall creatures gitte.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11867:5"/>
Thrice happie ſhee, for theſe in her remainde,</l>
            <l>As in her courſe of life was well explainde:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Morata</hi> ſhould her ſurname be by right,</l>
            <l>For ſhee with manners was moſt richly dight.</l>
            <l>Her body was a Temple, where did raigne</l>
            <l>The true tipes of a vertuous Soueraigne.</l>
            <l>Shee vtterly deteſted Romaine Lawes,</l>
            <l>The Popiſh Relickes, and the olde Prieſtes Sawes:</l>
            <l>The Trueth ſhe honour'd with vntaunted minde,</l>
            <l>And with Trueths girdle did her Loynes combinde.</l>
            <l>Worthy ſhe was to liue <hi>Sibillas</hi> dayes,</l>
            <l>Her worth did equallize <hi>Sibillas</hi> prayſe.</l>
            <l>Had the three Siſters which the life doth guide,</l>
            <l>Not mans felicitie ſo much enui'de:</l>
            <l>Yea, and againſt the Gods appoyntment toe,</l>
            <l>Attempt the thing they wiſht them not to doe:</l>
            <l>Loe, ſuch preheminence hath Deſtenies,</l>
            <l>To do what ſo they liſt (though <hi>Ioue</hi> denies.)</l>
            <l>See how the labouring Ant begins to droope,</l>
            <l>See how the loftie headed Stagge doth ſtoope,</l>
            <l>The Graſſe doth wither and the Fieldes waxe baire,</l>
            <l>The Birdes leaue ſinging, and Deteſt the aire</l>
            <l>And to the rockie clyſtes with ſpeed do flie,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11867:6"/>
And fraught with anguiſh do deſpaire, and die.</l>
            <l>Salt teares diſtill from all good Subiectes faces,</l>
            <l>Which on their cheekes make goodly milke-white traces</l>
            <l>Sables is common, and in eſtimation:</l>
            <l>He that wantes Sables is not in the faſhion.</l>
            <l>Why theſe are ſights well fitting my ſad ſpirit:</l>
            <l>Now ſhall my hart his long wiſht eaſe inherit,</l>
            <l>When euery creature doth conioyne in one,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Belphaebes</hi> parture from the world to mone.</l>
            <l>Shee is departed, dead, and gone long ſince,</l>
            <l>And hath in Heauen a place of recidence:</l>
            <l>From Earth ſhe came, and thither's gone againe;</l>
            <l>In Heauen ſhe is, and there ſhall ſtill remaine.</l>
            <l>O Virgin chaſt, O Phenix of thy kind,</l>
            <l>Which being gone, leaues not thy like behind.</l>
            <l>O Lampe of light, O Starre celeſtiall,</l>
            <l>Thy matchleſſe beautie was Angelicall,</l>
            <l>With thee did die the worldes felicitie:</l>
            <l>With thee decay'd all antique dignitie.</l>
            <l>She is captiued in an endleſſe Chaine,</l>
            <l>No hope of future comfort doth remaine.</l>
            <l>In her lay all mens hope and loue: ſhe dead,</l>
            <l>All hope and fauour is for euer fled:</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11867:6"/>
She was mens ioy, in her they onely ioy'd,</l>
            <l>By her departure, they are much anoy'd:</l>
            <l>Thus hope, and fauour, ioy, (yea euery bliſſe)</l>
            <l>Since her miſcariage, euer fair'd amiſſe.</l>
            <l>Let men and women breake their hartes with grones,</l>
            <l>Let Babes and Children ſpend the time in mones:</l>
            <l>Let ſorrows ſoppes mixt with a bitter gall,</l>
            <l>Suffize the hunger of both great and ſmall.</l>
            <l>Let teares diſtill, and ſtraine their tender partes,</l>
            <l>Let griefe be <hi>Nector</hi> to reioyce their hartes.</l>
            <l>No man ſuruiue that hath no teares to ſpende,</l>
            <l>He that doth weepe vntil his teares haue ende,</l>
            <l>Vnto the loweſt earth let him take way,</l>
            <l>And borrow teares of wofull <hi>Hecuba:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Which many Pooles hath cauſ'd to flow with teares,</l>
            <l>Since her laſt date of twiſe three hundred yeeres.</l>
            <l>Awake you Feendes, whoſe nature is to ſleepe:</l>
            <l>Awake I ſay, and ſtraine your ſelues to weepe:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Somnus</hi> ariſe, deaths meſſenger awake,</l>
            <l>And to ſome mournefull taſke your ſelues betake,</l>
            <l>The time commaundes, and time muſt be reſpected:</l>
            <l>Time cannot be recal'd that is neglected.</l>
            <l>You that haue all this while ſlept in a traunce,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11867:7"/>
Enwrapped in a cloude of ignoraunce,</l>
            <l>Hap'ly may thinke that cauſeleſſe I lament,</l>
            <l>And euery teare I ſhed is vainely ſpent:</l>
            <l>But know the cauſe: Eearthes ſoueraigne <hi>Queene</hi> is dead.</l>
            <l>Dead ſure ſhe is, imbalm'd, and wrapt in Lead:</l>
            <l>For this cauſe ſorrow, and lament with mee;</l>
            <l>Follow you after, Ile chiefe mourner be:</l>
            <l>My harts condolement ſhall excell you all,</l>
            <l>For it is made of Lyuer, more then Gall.</l>
            <l>Why, now you are compasſionate I ſee,</l>
            <l>I weepe before, you after ſeconde mee,</l>
            <l>And now you ſight, your colours come and go:</l>
            <l>A certaine figure of your inwarde woe.</l>
            <l>Now poaſte againe to <hi>Plutos</hi> regiment,</l>
            <l>Vnfold to him this ſodaine accident,</l>
            <l>Go Meſſenger of death, and <hi>Somnus</hi> Goe,</l>
            <l>Be you the meſſengers of pale fac'd woe:</l>
            <l>Let teares hereafter be your choyceſt drinke,</l>
            <l>With teares fill all your Riuers to the brinke.</l>
            <l>Let Heauen and Hell for euer mourne I ſay,</l>
            <l>Night be there euer, neuer be there day.</l>
            <l>Continue thus vntill the Fates relent,</l>
            <l>And ſhe from whence ſhe came aliue be ſent.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11867:7"/>
Mount winged Fame, and furrow through the aire,</l>
            <l>Make Heauen reſound with echoes of diſpaire:</l>
            <l>Proclayme ſadde tydinges of this luckleſſe chaunce,</l>
            <l>And with thy Trumpe awake dull ignoraunce.</l>
            <l>Sound loude, for he is deafe, and nothing knowes,</l>
            <l>He neuer greeues nor pines at anyes woes,</l>
            <l>He ſets, and neither ſtirres, nor ſpeakes whole dayes.</l>
            <l>He anſweres none, nor mindes what any ſayes.</l>
            <l>Not farre from <hi>Lethe</hi> this aged Sire doth dwell,</l>
            <l>This <hi>Lethe</hi> a ſpacious Riuer is in Hell,</l>
            <l>Whoſe nature is to dull the Memorie</l>
            <l>Of thoſe that drinke thereof; or dwelleth bie.</l>
            <l>Fame ſpread thy winges in Heauen, in Earth, in Hell,</l>
            <l>To euery miſter wite, her downefall tell.</l>
            <l>Come Sorrow come, and helpe me to lament,</l>
            <l>My fainting ſpirits now are almoſt ſpent:</l>
            <l>My ſpeech begins to fayle, my limbes waxe faint,</l>
            <l>Ere I aſcend the top of my complaint.</l>
            <l>Then heere Ile ſtay, in this darke vale Ile reſt,</l>
            <l>And in dum ſhewes my griefe ſhall be expreſt.</l>
            <l>Die hart with ſorrow and eternall paine,</l>
            <l>Vnleſſe <hi>Belphaebe</hi> do reuiue againe.</l>
            <l>Now whil'ſt <hi>Melpomene</hi> lay in a ſound,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11867:8"/>
Dewing with teares melancholy ground,</l>
            <l>His abſence was deplor'd on <hi>Parnaſſ</hi> hill,</l>
            <l>Teares did from euery Muſes eyes diſtill.</l>
            <l>Some in a furie rent their golden lockes,</l>
            <l>Some hang'd the head, ſome ſtampt, the breſt ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e knocks,</l>
            <l>Some inly ſigth, and others wrong their handes,</l>
            <l>To ſhew their ſtate wherein their ſorrow ſtandes,</l>
            <l>At length in ſecret Synod they decreed,</l>
            <l>To ſende <hi>Terpſicore</hi> abroad with ſpeed,</l>
            <l>To ſearch remote, and melancholy nookes:</l>
            <l>Which his ſad humour with contentment brookes,</l>
            <l>Much ground he trauerſt ouer hill, and daile<hi>:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Twas long eare aught his trauaile did auaile.</l>
            <l>Still as he went, vpon his Harpe he playde,</l>
            <l>By which <hi>Melpomene</hi> was much diſmayde,</l>
            <l>When as the ſound did to his hearing flie,</l>
            <l>For grieued mindes do Muſicke quite defie.</l>
            <l>At laſt directed by the powers Diuine,</l>
            <l>He ſaw whereas the wandring Muſe did pine:</l>
            <l>Goodly he louted, and ſoone him beſpake,</l>
            <l>That to <hi>Parnaſsus</hi> he would iourney make.</l>
            <l>To take poſſeſſion of his long voyde place,</l>
            <l>And liue among'ſt the reſt of heauenly race.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11867:8"/>
               <hi>Melpomene</hi> to him made no reply,</l>
            <l>But like a ſenceleſſe ſtone vpon the ground did lie,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Terpſicore</hi> with ſpeed flew backe againe,</l>
            <l>And tolde the Muſes of their brothers paine,</l>
            <l>Which he left ſpeechleſſe on the frigorous ground,</l>
            <l>Either quite dead, or in a deadly ſound.</l>
            <l>With that the Muſes much amazed flies</l>
            <l>Vnto the dwelling of the Deſtenies,</l>
            <l>To know their brothers ſodaine cauſe of griefe,</l>
            <l>And whether they would ſend his woes reliefe.</l>
            <l>The Fates recomforted their grieued hartes,</l>
            <l>And bade them neuer dread Deaths ſharpe poynt dartes:</l>
            <l>Tolde them at large, the cauſe of his lament,</l>
            <l>And how to giue his griefe a ſuddaine vent:</l>
            <l>Soone they tooke leaue, and to the place did flie,</l>
            <l>Where the ſadde Muſe lay wrapt in miſerie:</l>
            <l>They rubde his temples, lifted vp his head,</l>
            <l>In his pale face, pale death was figured,</l>
            <l>At length ſome ſparkes of life in him appeard,</l>
            <l>Which all their late dead hartes reuiu'd and chear'd.</l>
            <l>With chearefull words they chear'd him, and him prayde</l>
            <l>No more to grieue, no more to be diſmayde.</l>
            <l>The Fates (quoth they) in priuate ſo decreed,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11867:9"/>
That ſhe for whom thou weep'ſt, by death ſhould bleed,</l>
            <l>And they which by deaths cruell hand are ſlaine,</l>
            <l>Nor ſigthes, norſingulfes can reduce againe:</l>
            <l>And know, the Fates haue ſeated in her place,</l>
            <l>Though not a Woman, yet of heauenly race,</l>
            <l>A goodly KING, to be earthes Soueraigne:</l>
            <l>Which Iuſtice, Peace, and Vertue, will maintaine.</l>
            <l>Then ioy a new, recall thy wonted reſt:</l>
            <l>The Fates were kinde, that thee from death hath bleſt.</l>
            <l>Theſe wordes, his woe did ſomewhat mittigate,</l>
            <l>And he aſſum'd againe his former ſtate:</l>
            <l>With winges of ioy they furrowed through the ſkie,</l>
            <l>And ſoone ariued at <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> hie:</l>
            <l>Where now each Muſe enioyes his hartes content,</l>
            <l>Spending the time in wanton meriment:</l>
            <l>Thankes be to thoſe auſpicious powers aboue,</l>
            <l>That hath eſtabliſhed this concordant loue.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q xml:lang="lat">Mors ſeptra ligonibus equat.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:11867:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
